Welcome to the content
video for chapter 3.2 and
3.3 of your textbook,
Algorithms and Studio Code.
In the beginning of
chapter 3 here, we're going
to be going over some
high-level concepts.
So we'll get more into the
code a little bit later.
But for now, we're going
to go over algorithms.
And at a high level, what
an algorithm really is, is a
procedure for solving a problem
in terms of the actions.
kind of like it says here the
actions to execute in the order in
which these actions execute so
you've probably heard a lot of people
talk about like the algorithm
when they're talking about social
media tiktok instagram whatever it
might be and that's totally true
that there are algorithms in play
um to decide what gets put in front
of you um and and um well that
is true that that is algorithms
are also varied in their scope and
their capacity and what they do.
Another algorithm that's somewhat
well known is called Dijkstra's
algorithm. And I'll use that as
an example here. So Dijkstra's
algorithm is an algorithm that
determines the shortest path between
two destinations or two buildings
or whatever it might be. And
you probably use something similar
to Dijkstra's algorithm every
time you walk around on campus,
right? So if I was trying to go
over to Old Main on campus from my
office, my brain would automatically
calculate a set of steps for
me, right? So in order to get
to Old Main, I have to go out my
office door, walk down the hall,
go down a set of stairs,
exit the building
I'm currently in, walk across campus, and
get to Old Main, I'd probably walk
diagonally across the quad, right?
And that is because that is the
shortest path between those two points
right my office and Old Main and
what's what's interesting about this
is that my brain kind of automatically
knows that the order I need to
execute those steps as they get to
be right in front of me and it almost
like figures it out before I even
have to I don't even have to do any
like actual thinking there and so
that's just an example of an algorithm
it's really just a set of steps
saying here's what you need to do
and here's the order in which you
need to do them and so as you code
things you are going to essentially
be writing algorithms right you're
going to be writing steps for your
computer and you're going to be telling
your computer in which order they
need to calculate those steps so
that is algorithms and then pseudocode
it goes really well with algorithms
because what pseudocode is um it's
kind of scoping out your entire
algorithm before you write a lick
of code. I really like pseudocode
because it is, like it says in the
book, it's an informal English-like
language for thinking out loud or
thinking out your algorithms before you
write them. And it's kind of like
when you sit down to write an essay
or some kind of a story or a book,
whatever it might be, usually you
have some kind of a high-level idea
in your mind of how that story or
paper or whatever it might be is
supposed to go and I think we too often
as programmers make the mistake
of we sit down and we know what we
want to code and so we just start
coding and I think that is our biggest
pitfall as programmers is that we
never write things out ahead of
time so I like this example of
pseudocode that they have in the book
here's an algorithm that prompts
the user to enter two integers and
this is a fairly simple example
but just bear with me for a second
get two integers from the user
add them together and store them
and display their sum so here it
is written out in English prompt
the user to enter the first integer
input the first integer prompt
the user to enter the second input
the second add the first integer
to the second integer store the
sum and display the numbers now
you would probably never pseudo
code an example like this because
it's pretty simple but when you
get to something complicated like
building an app or a database or
running an algorithm that will
calculate the shortest distance
between two buildings, I don't know.
You don't want to just start coding.
You want to really map out the
variables that you might have,
what inputs you'll need, what
calculations you need to do. And
this really allows you to use all the
tools in your tool belt. And the
tools that you have are the things
that you're learning in this course
right now. So pseudocoding is
a really, really great and important
resource that most people don't
use and it could be your superpower
to becoming a really great
coder so that's everything for this
content video thanks for watching